A Guide to the Page Family Papers, 1819-1976
Virginia Historical Society
Letters from friends and family are scattered through 1904-1908; most family letters are from Rosewell, especially in 1905, sharing news from the mill and news of the corn, wheat, millet, and pea crops, cutting of timber, installing of a phone line, selling of lambs and wool, building of a dam on one of the Hanover County properties, and changes in tenants. Rosewell sent a six-month statement concerning all farm costs and asked Tom to pay various debts. Other family letters to Tom discuss his financing of schooling for Rosewell's daughter, Anne, and for a distant relative, Randolph Rosewell Page, at Virginia Polytechnic Institute. A cousin from Clifton Forge, Va., Lizzie R. Taylor, asked Tom for money to build a rectory. Strangers as well as friends wanted Tom to help them get jobs such as J. L. Hall, a professor at William and Mary College, who wanted a job at the University of North Carolina (7/7/04), or a law professor at Wake Forest College wanting Tom to go to the White House and ask the President to appoint him to a district court judgeship (12/16/08). Several letters in 1904 indicate that Tom was trying to influence the Library of Congress to hire Alexander Welbourne Weddell.
Notable letters to Tom in this time period came from Samuel Langhorne Clemens, thanking Florence and Tom for their kindness to his wife, who died in June 1904; from Thomas Nelson Carter about a land auction; and Teddy Roosevelt, who Carter would not vote for "on account of his putting forward the Negroes in the platform..." (6/24/04); from John Singleton Mosby concerning the Gettysburg campaign (10/26/08); from Ernest Thompson Seton, an animal painter, lecturer, and adventurer (12/8/08); and from Victor Howard Metcalf, lawyer and Secretary of the Navy, thanking Tom for a copy of his work on Robert E. Lee.
The last box of Thomas Nelson Page correspondence dates from 1909 to 1922. The usual pattern of letters prevails here but noteworthy letters follow. Leonard Gunnell, a cousin by marriage, worked at the Smithsonian Institution and sent Tom a picture of the old home at Oakland (1/09). (Oakland burned in 1899 and was rebuilt in six months.) Also, in January 1909, Tom received letters about horses he can buy in Vermont and Virginia. Cyrus Hall McCormick, son of the inventor, sends Tom a book about the Southern black; "...I send it herewith, knowing that you, who understand so thoroly [sic] the old-time life of the Southern negro...(2/3/09)." From Lexington, Ky., Foxhall A. Daingerfield writes Tom his impressions of Robert E. Lee, who he knew personally during the Civil War (2/8/09). In September 1909, Charles Scribner's Sons enclosed a contract for publication of John Marvel, Assistant.
In 1912 there were many letters from Ruth (Nelson) Page to Tom. It appears Ruth was helping Rosewell with the management of Oakland and other properties owned or subsidized by Tom. Rosewell campaigned and won the election to become the second auditor of Virginia. He served in that post until 1928; thus, much of his time was spent in Richmond. Ruth's letters describe family and farm news, especially the health and death of her mother-in-law, Elizabeth Burwell (Nelson) Page. Rosewell still wrote Tom on a few occasions, but the remainder of the 1912 letters are sympathy letters from strangers, friends, and family concerning Elizabeth's death. A few thank-you notes from distant cousins discuss Tom's kindness in paying their school tuition.
From 1913 to 1917 there are only twenty items, mainly letters from Ruth and Rosewell. Ruth praised Tom upon becoming the U.S. Ambassador to Italy. Ruth and Rosewell's daughter, Anne (Page) Johns, wrote her uncle from Stuart Hall School, Staunton, Va.; Tom financed this niece's education. For a number of years, there was a school run at "Oakland," and Ruth mentioned "our academy" in her February 20, 1916 letter. Also, in 1916, Jonathan Daniels, Secretary of the Navy, wrote Tom about the Federal Reserve Act (5/12/16). Walter Hines Page, a cousin and an editor at Doubleday, Page and Co., Long Island, N.Y., informed Tom of changes in their personnel, resulting in delays dealing with his book (unidentified) (1/19/13). From 1918 until Tom's death in 1922, correspondence is slim, numbering thirty-two items. The effects of World War I are quite evident in letters to Tom in 1918. H. Rozier Dulany, a real estate agent in Washington, D.C., wrote Tom about a tenant's rent, travels to Tom's farms in Virginia, selling Tom's cattle, and the "scarcity of farm labor in Virginia" (1/1/18). Several of Ruth's letters discussed the effects of the war, especially her letter of June 23, 1918. Her April 1918 letters dwell on the death of Frank Page, Tom's older brother. In September, Ruth explained her move to Richmond where her daughter Anne is working for the war effort, postponing her education until after the war. In October, Ruth discussed the Spanish flu epidemic in Richmond, and in November, Ruth described the impact on Richmond of returning soldiers. Anne wrote her uncle on October 20 explaining the nature of her war job at the bag-loading plant, mentioning measuring black powder for ammunition. Rosewell wrote Tom in Italy in February 1919, "You have filled one of the most difficult posts in the world with dignity and honor...." In one of Tom's last letters, he wrote to "Lil Gals," probably his step-daughters, mentioning he had to borrow money to carry on at York Harbor, Maine (9/18/21).
Thomas Nelson Page materials also include financial records consisting of receipts or bills for office supplies, crops such as oats and hay, farm equipment, lumber, hardware, freight charges from Europe, but mainly, royalty payments from Charles Scribner's Sons.
Among Page's miscellaneous materials are three certificates, 1874-1877, from the University of Virginia for Tom's having passed courses in law, and there is a commission for Page having attained the rank of 1st Lieutenant of the Richmond Light Infantry Blues.
Scattered papers refer to cases Tom handled when he practiced law in Richmond, Va. Other notable papers give Rosewell the power-of-attorney (1913) for Tom and include a copy of Tom's will (1922).
Among the last items in this series are newspaper articles about Tom, including a description of his funeral service in 1922. Also present are pictures, 1919-1921, including one that is undated but identified a dress that belonged to Elizabeth (Burwell) Nelson. The caption on this picture says the dress was kept at "Oakland" and, thus, was lost when the house burned in 1899. Photographs taken in 1919 document Italian troops guarding the American Embassy and concern Italian Premier Vittorio Orlando's return from the Paris peace conference. Another photograph shows Tom and Rosewell in Denver, Colo. Finishing the series are two undated addresses concerning the history of the settlement of Jamestown and the commemoration of the Virginia Convention of 1776. A speech, probably written by Tom, dated 1906, was given in Lisbon for the American Legation, and concerns the medical profession. Miscellaneous papers include the wedding announcement (1886) for Tom's first marriage to Anne Seddon (Bruce) Page, a sonnet (undated) to Amelie Louise (Rives) Chandler Troubetzkoy written on reading her "Grief and Faith", recent news (1919) about Yugoslavia as reported in the Italian press, an essay (undated) about Page and "Marse Chan," an invitation list (undated) for a dinner, probably given in honor of Jonathan Daniels at the American Embassy in Italy, and notes (undated) about On Newfound River, written in memory of Annie.
Series Eight contains the papers of Anne Seddon (Bruce) Page (1867-1888), known as "Annie," Thomas Nelson Page's first wife. Her correspondence is mainly from family and friends, including her parents, brothers, and sisters, who share family happenings and alwayed praise Tom and his writing. William Cabell Bruce, a brother, described his life as a lawyer in Baltimore, Md., in November 1882, while Charles Bruce, her father, wrote about his daily routine at "Staunton Hill, Charlotte County, Va., in March 1887. From 1885 to 1888, James Douglas Bruce, another of her brothers, wrote Annie while he lived abroad in Germany and France. Family included Thomas Nelson Carter, who was a cousin of Annie's and the law partner of her husband, and Tom's aunt, Anne Rose Page. In December 1886, she wrote Annie a story about a black child brought up by a white woman in Goochland County, Va. He murdered the woman when he turned eighteen because she would not buy him a certain pair of shoes. Anne Rose also commented on Tom's writings. Friends such as Lelia Augusta (Myers) Morgan wrote in August 1886, about the earthquake in Richmond, Va., while Annie and Tom are on their European honeymoon. In February 1887, an unidentified correspondent wrote from England mentioning a dinner she attended where several artists were present including James Abbott McNeill Whistler.
Series Nine includes correspondence exists between Florence (Lathrop) Field Page (1858-1921), Thomas Nelson Page's second wife, and Rosewell Page, Ruth (Nelson) Page, Anne (Page) Johns, all relatives of Tom, and Florence's grandson by her daughter Minna (Field) Gibson Burnaby, Henry Field (originally named Henry Gibson). Henry wrote from England and described the Christmas activities around him in 1908. A few letters to Florence relate to financial transactions or obtaining a tutor for one of Flo's daughters. Also included are accounts, 1897-1900, in part pertaining to paying a tutor and to a purchase at a home furnishings store in Washington, D.C.
Series 10 begins with the correspondence, 1888-1938, of Rosewell Page (1858-1939). Half of Rosewell's correspondence comes from family or friends and half from business acquaintances. Aunt Anne Rose Page, along with Rosewell's mother, write him about the death in 1893 of Frank's baby, Rose, and affairs at Oakland. Ruth, his wife, gives him news of their children and Rosewell's parents and requests various things for Rosewell to bring from Richmond. Elizabeth Hope Stewart of "Brook Hill" sends him congratulations for his marriage to Ruth in 1898. Other folks compliment him on becoming a member of the Virginia House of Delegates and express sympathy in the loss of Tom's two wives. While Anne (Page) Johns attends Stuart Hall School, Staunton, Va., Rosewell writes his daughter about family news.
As a member of the law firm of Rutherfoord and Page, Richmond, Va., Rosewell received legal letters related to cases he handled, but much of his business correspondence related to either his biography of his brother Tom or Tom's publications. From 1922-1937, Charles Scribner's Sons corresponded with Rosewell about publishing his biography of Tom, royalty payments for at least 28 of Tom's publications, renewing copyright on one of Tom's stories, asking Rosewell's permission to publish a new edition of Two Little Confederates, arranging a special educational edition of Red Rock, and concerning movie rights for Tom's works. In 1934, Lola D. Moore, a representative for authors and artists in Hollywood and Beverly Hills, Calif., corresponded with Rosewell wanting to market Red Rock in the movie industry. Another agent, Grace Morse of New York, also wrote Rosewell about trying to sell movie rights. Other business letters refer to "Oakland" and the surrounding area in Hanover County, Va., including building of a bridge across the South Anna River and placement of telephone lines through Page property.
The remainder of the series includes accounts, 1897-1927, including five notes (1905) on the school account for Hall's Free School run by Miss Orr and, probably, sponsored by the Page family; notes on logging expenses (no date); accounts between Tom and Rosewell concerning farm expenses in 1907-1908; and a royalty report for Tom's publication for 1927. Also included are undated manuscripts, including a draft of Rosewell's Hanover County: Its History and Legends and Thomas Nelson Page: A Memoir of a Virginia Gentleman. A draft of a speech about Jamestown filed in Series 7.7 possibly was by Rosewell also. Lastly, miscellaneous materials, 1868-1916, include an undated newspaper picture of Rosewell, his wife and daughter, and others attending a memorial observance of Edgar Allan Poe's birthday, and a biographical sketch and picture of Rosewell.
Ruth (Nelson) Page's papers make up Series 11. Most of Ruth's correspondence is found in earlier series of her mother-in-law, Elizabeth Burwell (Nelson) Page, her brother-in-law, Thomas Nelson Page, and her husband, Rosewell Page. Other family letters found here include those from Minna (Field) Gibson Burnaby, Thomas Nelson Page's step-daughter, about a visit to "Rock Ledge," York Harbor, Maine, and of Ruth's son, Robert Nelson Page. One letter by this son was written in August 1921, from "Rock Ledge." In October 1918, Mary C. Nelson, Ruth's sister who served as a Red Cross nurse during World War I, wrote from Paris. John Cook Wyllie, Director of Libraries at the University of Virginia, addressed Ruth in July 1967, discussing the acquisition of Thomas Nelson Page papers.
Series 12 contains materials of Anne Page. In 1914, Anne Page, daughter of Rosewell and Ruth Page, attended Stuart Hall School in Staunton, Va., and she wrote her brother, Robert Nelson Page. During World War I, Anne was back in the Richmond area working for the war effort at DuPont Engineering Co.; this company sent congratulations to its workers, including Anne, on November 14, 1918. Anne wrote Karl E. Johnson at the Red Cross headquarters in Petersburg, also in 1918, asking if she and the Hall's Free School, probably run under the auspices of the Page family at "Oakland," could open a canteen on the Richmond-Washington Highway to serve soldiers. (Then, during World War II, Anne received a letter from Richmond Filter Center thanking its workers for their help in wartime.) From 1929-1941, Anne received letters from the national Junior League Magazine concerning articles that she wrote for this publication. William B. Thalhimer, Jr., wrote in April 1951, about wanting to honor her as one of Richmond's noted authors. From 1967-1969, Anne received letters from various persons associated with the University of Virginia concerning the sale of Thomas Nelson Page manuscripts to the college.
Anne (Page) Johns's materials also include an annual report for 1930-1931, an undated constitution, copies of The Leaguer from May 1929-June 1931, and drafts of historical articles on the Junior League of Richmond; and war ration books from World War II.
One of two letters to Frank Stoddert Johns (1884-1971), husband of Anne (Page) Johns, arrived in April 1953, from an assistant to the Ambassador of Italy, thanking Dr. Johns for his courtesies when the assistant visited Virginia at the centennial celebration of the birth of Thomas Nelson Page. Other Frank Johns materials include a war ration book from World War II, an undated news article concerning the receipt of a portrait of Dr. Johns at Hampden-Sydney College, and a 1950 article about the college naming an auditorium for him. Johns had served as chairman of the Board of Trustees since 1938.
Section 14 concerns Julien Harrison Hill (1877-1943), father-in-law of Ruth Nelson (Johns) Hill, daughter of Anne (Page) Johns and Frank Stoddert Johns. Four scrapbooks trace Hill's life, beginning as a student in Petersburg, and following him throughout his career. The first volume, dated 1896-1942, includes a catalogue for the 1895-1896 session of the University School in Richmond, Va., the school first started in Petersburg, Va., by William Gordon McCabe. Hill is listed as a student. Hill participated in sports activities at the University School, as well as in college at the University of Virginia, which he entered in 1897. The baseball team schedule for 1898 includes a picture of the team. After Hill's college years, he continued to enjoy sports as noted in this scrapbook. One article dated April 11, 1942, concerns Hill's son, William M. Hill, captain of the University of Virginia football team.
The second volume of Hill's scrapbooks, dated 1904-1943, focuses on Hill's adult civic and social activities such as his membership in the Commonwealth Club and the Richmond German, efforts to get more playgrounds across Virginia, service as a member of the Civilian Examining Committee for the U.S. War Department in 1918 and a member of the Board of Managers of the Richmond Male Orphan Society in 1919. In the nineteen twenties he served on the Medical College of Virginia Board of Visitors, and in 1936, he was a director of the Chesapeake and Potomac Telephone Co. On December 17, 1940, Lady Nancy Witcher (Langhorne) Shaw Astor wrote Hill after he sent a group contribution to relieve the Air Raid distress. Personal asides include information about the death of his mother, Frances Cadwallader (Harrison) Hill, in 1916, and the death of his father, William Maury Hill, in 1918, about the wedding of his daughter, Diana Kearny (Hill) Patterson, in 1940, and about the death of Hill, himself, in 1943.
In the scrapbook for 1904-1943 Hill documented the progress of his adult career. In his young adult years, he served as assistant cashier at the National State Bank in Richmond and then, in 1915, he became a director of the National State and City Bank, later known as the State-Planters Bank and Trust Company. In 1917 he was still cashier but was elected to be a vice-president, and in 1920, he became president of the bank. A 1920 article by Hill appeared in the Journal of Accountancy. Hill became president of Old Dominion Trust Co. in 1922. Other news articles highlight his membership in professional groups such as the American Bankers Association, his service on the Advisory Committee of the Richmond Loan Agency of the Reconstruction Finance Corporation in 1932, and his appointment by President Franklin D. Roosevelt to his Advisory Committee on Works Allotment in 1935. Enclosures are dated 1939 and concern Hill's wife, Lucy, and the birth of their seventh child, Diana Kearny (Hill) Patterson. There are photographs and negatives of Diana and other siblings.
The last volume of the scrapbooks, dated 1914-1917, concerns Hill's appointment and service as the chief of staff of the Governor of Virginia, Henry Carter Stuart. The letter from Stuart offering the position to Hill is in the scrapbook as well as articles about Stuart. Also included are other newspaper articles about Hill's professional and civic activities.
Among Hill's miscellany are the certificate signed by Governor Stuart, making Hill his chief of staff, along with a memorial editorial of December 2, 1943, celebrating the life of Hill.
Lucy Colder De Lancey (Kearny) Hill materials include letters congratulating Lucy, wife of Julien Harrison Hill, on the birth of Diana Kearny (Hill) Patterson.
Series Sixteen includes correspondence of extended family members in the Bruce, Field, Johns, Lathrop, Nelson, Points, and Page families. Notable letters include an undated Civil War letter from a hospital at Warm Springs, Va. from a preacher who writes about how hard it is to console the sick soldiers and a January 3, 1864 letter from Stevenson Points to Lizzie Stevenson when he was a prisoner at Fort Delaware, Del. At the death of Anne Seddon (Bruce) Page in December 1888, members of the Bruce family receive sympathy letters. In January 1891, George Washington Points corresponded with Mary C. Nelson about the genealogy of the Points (also known as Poyntz) family. Bryan Lathrop, brother of Florence (Lathrop) Field Page, admonished Minna (Field) Gibson Burnaby about the status of her finances in 1912. Mary C. Nelson, sister of Ruth (Nelson) Page and Red Cross nurse during World War I, wrote an interesting letter in November 1918, about the ending of the war and the reactions in Paris. A last notable letter (undated) was written from Scotland to Miss Bessie (otherwise unidentified) and is from Johannes Wolf, a musicologist specializing in medieval music.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged in sixteen sections by main entry and further subdivided by subject or record type where necessary.
Index Terms
Authors, American -- Virginia -- History.; China -- Social life and customs -- 1644- 1912.; Diaries -- China -- Shanghai -- History -- 19th century.; Diaries -- Connecticut -- Woodbury -- History -- 19th century.; Diaries -- Virginia -- Hanover County -- History -- 20th century.; Education -- China -- History -- 19th century.; Episcopal Church -- Connecticut -- Clergy -- History -- 19th century.; Episcopal Church -- Virginia -- History.; Family -- Virginia -- Social life and customs.; Farm management -- Virginia -- History..; Hanover County (Va.) - - Social life and customs.; Laity -- Eipscopal Church -- Virginia.; Missionaries -- China -- History -- 19th century.; Mothers and sons -- Virginia -- History.; Nelson, Robert, 1819-1886.; Oakland (Hanover County, Va.); Page, Elizabeth Burwell Nelson, 1821-1912.; Page family.; Page, Rosewell, 1858-1939.; Page, Thomas Nelson, 1853-1922.; Virginia -- Social life and customs.; Women -- Virginia -- Family relationships.; Women -- Virginia -- Social life and customs.
Contents List
- Francis Page (1780-1849) loose accounts (Box 1)
- Francis Page (1780-1849) loose accounts (Box 1)
- John Page (1821-1901) correspondence (Box 1 (cont.))
- Elizabeth Burwell (Nelson) Page (1821-1912) papers
  - Diary (Box 1 (cont.))
  - Correspondence (Box 2-3)
- Robert Nelson (1819-1886) papers (Box 4)
- Rose (Points) Nelson (1827-1885) papers (Box 4 (cont.))
- Francis Page (1849-1918) papers (Box 4 (cont.))
- Thomas Nelson Page (1853-1922) papers
  - Correspondence (undated, 1861-1887) (Box 5-11)
  - Accounts
  - Certificates (Box 12 (cont.))
  - Legal papers (Box 12 (cont.))
  - Newspaper articles (Box 12 (cont.))
  - Pictures (Box 12 (cont.))
  - Speeches (Box 12 (cont.))
  - Miscellany (Box 12 (cont.))
- Anne Seddon (Bruce) Page (1867-1888) correspondence (Box 13)
- Florence (Lathrop) Field Page (1858-1921) papers (Box 13 (cont.))
  - Correspondence (Box 13 (cont.))
  - Accounts (Box 13 (cont.))
- Rosewell Page (1858-1939) papers (Box 13 (cont.))
  - Correspondence (Box 13 (cont.))
  - Accounts (Box 14)
  - Manuscripts (Box 14 (cont.))
  - Miscellany
- Ruth (Nelson) Page (1871-1975?) correspondence (Box 14 (cont.))
- Anne (Page) Johns (b. 1899) papers
  - Correspondence (Box 15)
  - Junior League papers (Box 15 (cont.))
  - Miscellany
- Frank Stoddert Johns (1884-1971) papers
  - Correspondence (Box 15 (cont.))
  - Miscellany (Box 15 (cont.))
- Julien Harrison Hill (1877-1943) papers
  - Corresopondence (Box 16 (cont.))
  - Scrapbook (Box 16 (cont.))
  - Scrapbook
  - Scrapbook
- Lucy Colder De Lancey (Kearny) Hill (b. 1881) portions of scrapbook (Box 18 (cont.))
- Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 18 (cont.))